<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The interest of creditors and debtors, or the duty that is incumbent on both, by the laws moral, civil, and divine. With their respective interest stated. Published, for their mutual benefit, by an impartial observer of the often severity of the former, and defection of the latter</title>
            <author>P. P.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91549</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P93A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229888</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895719</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895719</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153255</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91549)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153255)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2357:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The interest of creditors and debtors, or the duty that is incumbent on both, by the laws moral, civil, and divine. With their respective interest stated. Published, for their mutual benefit, by an impartial observer of the often severity of the former, and defection of the latter</title>
                  <author>P. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 8-31 [i.e. 34] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, and are to be sold by William Rawlins over against the Royal Exchange in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: P.P.</note>
                  <note>P. 34 misnumbered 31, and vice versa.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Debtor and creditor --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Interest --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153255:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE INTEREST OF Creditors AND Debtors, OR The Duty that is Incumbent on both, By the Laws Moral, Civil, and Divine.</p>
            <p>With their Reſpective Intereſt Stated.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed, for their Mutual Benefit, by an Impartial Obſerver of the often Severity of the Former, and Defection of the Latter</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>William Rawlins</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:153255:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153255:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Mr Sympathy with poor Priſoners hath incited me to offer the following Diſcourſe in their behalf; that it might provoke the Charity of Men, or at leaſt the Clemency and forbearance of their Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors towards them in this, or that I hope it may meet with ſome ſucceſs, although it be a flinty Age. And if the reaſon thereof prevail with any, to adminiſter their ſuperfluities, and improve their
<pb facs="tcp:153255:3"/>Reſpective Capacities, for the alleviation of Priſoners Burthens; not deſpairing of thy ſelf for one; then my deſign herein will not be fruſtrated, who am.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, P. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:153255:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The INTEREST</hi> OF Creditors AND Debtors.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat it is a Duty incumbent upon Humanity to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Good of its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuals; and recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally every individual one the others good; or they violate the Harmony of their being, ſeems to be the intent of that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153255:4"/>Maxim, <hi>Nemo ſibi naſcitur,</hi> that no man is born to himſelf. And becauſe ſuch Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons remain in Nature, notwithſtanding the inundation of Ignorance by the Apoſtacy: a greater improvement is expected from us, under thoſe many advantages, ſince of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for our Reſtoration. The firſt Branch of ſelf-hood (the root of all Strife, Debate, Contentions, Injuries, Homicides, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) appeared in the Fratricide of <hi>Cain,</hi> who perpetrated that Act upon his Brother, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſingle Emulation of his Offering be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſpected; but hath ſince, Spawned a multitude of Iniquities in the World. As men hath given liberty to their Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Appetites, and might be traced to be the Mother of moſt (if not all) Enormities committed, whereof the cruelty and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of Creditors exerciſed towards their Debtors, by Arreſts, Impriſonments, and other Depredations made upon their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Eſtates, is none of the ſmalleſt Bratts: And that the deformity thereof may appear, is the deſigned appropriate Subject of this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Now therefore all ſuch as are, or may be concerned; let them conſider, that a rigorous proceeding of Creditors againſt their Debtors, is not encouraged or counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced, by any Laws Moral, Civil, or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153255:4"/>no rule of Manners, dictates of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, or divine Precept, doth favour, but rather frown upon ſo degenerate an Act. A <hi>Bay</hi> of the uncontaminated Nature, was illuſtrated by <hi>Abram,</hi> who might have chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged <hi>Lot</hi> in right of Anceſtry: A priori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Election, as may particularly be ſeen in the Story,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.</note> and was before the Moral Law was Exhibited; ſo great a Patriarch and Potentate being indiſputably a pattern of Patience, ſelf-denial and Brotherhood, for the imitation of all his Survivors. The good that <hi>Joſeph</hi> returned his Brethren for their Evil, with many the like Preſidents in Holy Writ that might be inſtanced, ſufficiently commend to men the Exerciſe of Patience, Goodneſs and Charity one towards another.</p>
            <p>If we reſpect the Decalogue, which was added for the Reſtitution of the Original Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the ſeverity of a Creditor to his Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, is far from being juſtified thereby; And without doubt, is implicitly forbid in the Sixt Commandment: <hi>Thou ſhalt do no Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> which comprehends a great deal more then barely violence to a mans life, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many wayes to render that inſupportable or very miſerable: Among which, the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor purſuing his Debtor to Priſon, may well be reputed one, where he is made uſeleſs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153255:5"/>to his Generation, in all his Capacities; he cannot there ſerve himſelf, leſs his Family, and leaſt of all his King and Countrey, to whom the greater Obligation lyes. I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all ſober men, whether ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition be not Equivolent to death it ſelf, to any man that yet retains judgement, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe it its proper merit. The Scriptures in divers places, give teſtimony and rebuke to the ſecret practiſes of men, one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and moſt of all, being ſhrowded under a Cloak of Juſtice: And here it may be a digreſſion eaſily pardonable, to inſpect thoſe Imployments and Profeſſions of men, that in ſome meaſure do participate of the Nature (and are ſubſervient to the ends) of ſuch a murdering Spirit.</p>
            <p>It will not be improper to begin with thoſe that are the Agents and Factors for Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, in the Rigor and Violence they uſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Debtors; and the firſt ſort of them, are ſome perſons appending to the Law, who take pleaſure to act to the undo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man, becauſe they are hired to it, and it is very comely and honourable, they think, to be the miniſters of Malice and Revenge, becauſe they are paid for it; a ſort of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinary people like Packhorſes to any deſign for Money, as the late Rebellious Age too wofully exemplified.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:153255:5"/>
            <p>The blood of the Degenerate nature, is highly vitiated in them, who help the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil at a dead lift, doing that for him which he can't do for himſelf: being Reſtrained from doing men that Evil he wills, he incites a Civil War in their Species, whereby to hurt one another, not unlike that Proverb, <hi>Homo homini Daemon,</hi> the Exaction, Infidelity, and Corruption of ſome of them, the ignorance and negligence of others towards their Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, are manifeſt Characters of a Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring quality, and unworthy management of a Profeſſion, in it ſelf ſufficiently neceſſary and juſtifiable.</p>
            <p>Theſe doubtleſs, if the life-blood were Money, and they could come as eaſily to the Purſe, as now they do, would make no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to cut the ſtrings, to gratifie their unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable deſire; when poor men are thus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and proſtrate to the Revenge of their Blood-thirſty Creditors, being caſt into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and made Tributary to the Drones of the Earth, <hi>Viz.</hi> their reſpective Keepers, Waiters, Turn-keys, Porters, <hi>cum multis aliis quos nunc preſcribere lougum est,</hi> their bones are there to be pick'd, while fit for lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, elſe but to make Dice of; a Phraſe too frequently uſed and tantamount effected, by ſome implacable Spirits upon their Debtors. Now not to ſtray too remotely from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153255:6"/>Subject; if we conſider the reſpective condition and capacity of Creditors, with that of their Debtors, their violent and rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Proſecution of them to Priſon, purſuing that alſo to the extremity of reſtraint, envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their leaſt Liberty, affording more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and benefit to their Dogs, then to ſuch men, whoſe misfortune hath been to incurr their debt; ſuch procedure is altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with Reaſon, and prejudicial to their own Intereſt. The condition of the one is abounding, the other neceſſitous and wanting, thus it ſtands with the Major part of Creditors and Debtors, the diſproporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſubſiſtance being ſufficiently evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, the one flouriſhing the other indigent; the Creditor making uſe of his plenty, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feeble and render his Debtor more inſolvent: this they do (though perhaps will or may be aſhamed to own it) to that end. What rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then hath Plenty to proſecute Poverty, when we conſider that one and the ſame hand diſpenſeth both,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.3.</note> as is atteſted by the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>Agur.</hi> Some are inevitably made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvent by Providence,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Proverbs,</hi> 30.8.</note> either by adjacent or remote means, whoſe Calamity is aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated to be then in Debt, and this condition which requires the more compaſſion, is made the opportunity of cruel Creditors to add to their miſery: without doubt ſuch perſons
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153255:6"/>would be as ready to affront their Creator (if within their reach) upon many croſs oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences of their intereſt, who ſo readily lay load upon his Creatures, their brethren,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.31.</note> for the Trifles of this world, wherein at the ſame time themſelves abound. The reaſon of all Actions is manifeſt by their end, by which it will appear, that the murdering proceedings of Creditors againſt their Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, are to gratify ſome domineering Luſt or other; to which all other Licentious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of men, are moſtly ſubſervient and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butary; ſome are precipitated thereunto, by Pride and inſolence, ſome by Paſſion, and Revenge, others by Pollicy, (who would ſhew themſelves wiſer than theirs fellowes, aiming to be firſt ſerved) and moſt if not all of them, are ſet on work by that Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Infernal Field, Covetouſneſs; men being thus acted by one Devil or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whoſe proper names are more obſcure; the Reaſon that guides them to ſuch inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane practiſes, is not that which was firſt given, but hath been ſince infected, and is become Earthly, ſenſual and Devilliſh. They flatter themſelves, ſtifling the rebukes of Conſcience, and hardning their hearts with the pretence of Juſtice, that a man may innocently ſeek his own, by ſuch ways and means as the Law provides him: to remove
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153255:7"/>which ſtone, there was a Maxim long ſince provided, <hi>viz. Omne nimium vertitur in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> Juſtice may be exacted with intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble circumſtances, which is ſo often forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the Levitical Law under the denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Oppreſſion;<note place="margin">19. <hi>Levit.</hi> 18 33, 34. <hi>ver.</hi>
               </note> and ſeemeth to be chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly, if not only meant, that for which a man may have ſome pretence, or colour of Juſtice, to act againſt his Brother. Whatſoever is rigorouſly required of diſabled correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, is of near kin to Oppreſſion, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deviating from that Royal Law implanted in Nature, and ſo frequently reinforced both in the Old and New Teſtament, <hi>of loving our Neighbor as our ſelf, and doing as we would be done unto;</hi> men that are willing to indulge themſelves in the practiſe of cruelty, have the impudence to aſſert, that they do nothing but what they ſhould willingly ſubmit unto and juſtify in their Creditors: willingly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing their own ſouls of all mercy, ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and humanity that ſhould adorn them, and cheating themſelves with a lye at the ſame time, being in a condition greatly above the ſufferer: they chooſe to be ignorant, that he that doth not eſpouſe the condition of the paſſive, can never charitably or juſtly mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure out unto him. Such indeed who have made their minds the manſion of all Beſtial qualities, may repute it ſeaſonable to ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153255:7"/>a man already under affliction: <hi>David</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of ſuch in the 10.17. &amp; 35. <hi>Pſalms.</hi> There needs no pains to deſcribe the uncomelineſs thereof, the actions of Boys in the Street one towards another, ſufficiently explode it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting in their Coverſation, the ſtriking of one that is down. Its impoſſible to derive ſuitable goodneſs, without a compaſſionate ſoul. There are another ſort of men, that have a little more tincture of Lenity, but yet are perſwaded to ſmother it, under pretence that Charity ſhould begin at home, they have a Family to maintain, and Children to raiſe Portions for, therefore they are obliged to be ſevere with their Debtors. This Cloak hath a plauſible Aſpect, but upon examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion 'twill be found as deformed as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; for were ſuch excuſe to be admitted as reaſonable, it would be a bar to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Charity amongſt men, that a man ſhould ſuſpend all acts of Goodneſs and Bounty, to preſeny and worthy objects there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, becauſe his children may have need of the ſame ten or twenty years afterward, is too great a ſparke of Infidely, a preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon providence and a Monopolizing of all benefits to his own Loyns, deſtructive to humane Society, inverting the deſign of the Creation, which by mutual help was to abound in the common Good. That grand
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153255:8"/>root Covetouſneſs before ſpoken off, doth alſo produce this branch, according to what is hinted in the <hi>Wiſdom of Solomon, that the wandring of Concupiſcence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>doth undermine the ſimple minde.</hi> Having thus far endeavoured the diſcovery of the unreſonableneſs of the cruel Creditors: here is opportunity alſo to induce the demonſtration, that ſuch his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings are againſt the reaſon of his own intreſt; to demonſtrate which, we are to conſider the Debtor under a double qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification, either honeſt or diſhoneſt: in both which denominations, the violent dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Creditor with his Debtor, is againſt the requiring of his own intereſt, which is, to be ſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied, if his Debtor be honeſt? greater ſecurity cannot be given him, then ſuch principles as will certainly perform, when ever Ability concurs: and to uſe force againſt ſuch an one whoſe power is abſent, may irritate and incenſe the Divine anger, that is jealous to revenge the cauſe of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent; and may render him Culpable of that Judgement denounced in the <hi>Pſalmes: His miſchief ſhall return upon his own head, and his violent dealing ſhall come down upon his own pate.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.16.</note> If the Debtor be diſhoneſt, conceales his ſtrength, can, but will not pay, although it can hardly be preſumed, that men ſhould chooſe a Priſon, and therewith a ſuperfluous
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153255:8"/>expence that doth accompany it, which in ſome reaſonable time, and their liberty might be ſaved, and conduce at leaſt towards ſatisfaction of the Creditors: yet admitting that ſuch there be, as many others that do things as inconſiſtant with reaſon, however it is the Creditors intereſt to forbare the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit; a Priſon generally debaucheth mens parts, and impoveriſheth their Purſe, which needs muſt diſappoint the hopes any man may have of payment from ſuch a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: A poor and unworthy revenge to be continued, unbefitting any that are Prudent or Pious, wherein their ends are fruſtrated in their life, and in their death muſt be worſe diſturbed, it being doubtleſs a great ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Reſt and Peace, to be the irrevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable cauſe of anothers miſery. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture adviſeth <hi>not to let the Sun go down upon our wrath,</hi> which implicitly forbids our dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the paths of revenge, of the leaſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs.</p>
            <p>There are a third ſort, and they will plead neceſſity for their excuſe, their own wants are ſo preſſing, that they muſt needs be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere with their Debtors: Theſe of all others are leaſt pardonable, that will aggravate their own miſery, to make another like them and paſt hopes to help them; whereas there is no neceſſity to evil Actions, and all that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153255:9"/>deviate from charity, are ſuch,
<hi>Solomon</hi> gives you a character of them <hi>Proverbs.</hi> 28.3. <hi>A poor man that oppreſſeth the poor, is like a ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping rain which leaveth no food.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>there is a Reciprocal and Correlate duty between Creditors and Debtors, as it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon one to exerciſe Forbearance and Patience, it is alſo upon the other, to be juſt and to pay as he is able; If men would think themſelves (as indeed they are) as accountable to <hi>God Almighty,</hi> for the omiſſion of theſe Duties, as for the breach of other his Commandments: Truly the Lawyers would have no ſuch cauſe to laugh at their Clyents follies, and wallow in the wealth of their Ruins.</p>
            <p>It remaineth now to Evidence, that the whole current of divine Precepts, is in the Pentateuch or Five books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo the days of the Prophets were full of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, the Doctrine of Chriſt himſelf and his Appoſtles, more abundantly is againſt, ſo unnatural, ungodly, and unchriſtain-like dealing of Creditors with their Debtors. <hi>Thou ſhalt not avenge, nor bare any grudge againſt the children of thy People,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.18.</note> 
               <hi>but thou ſhalt love thy Neighbor as thy Self, &amp;c.</hi> This Text preſuppoſes men to be offenders one againſt the other, either in their natural, or civil capacities, or both:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153255:9"/>And therefore commands them not to ſeek revenge, yea more, not to harbour the leaſt Animoſity each to other, with an affirmative Precept adjoyned, as the reaſon of the former; <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbor as thy ſelf:</hi> there is no man that hath yet a ſpark of Goodneſs remaining, but in any treſpaſs he commits, or may commit, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt God or man, but he would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly be forgiven, or at leaſt forborn, till he can make a juſt Reconciliation; And he that thus loves himſelf,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 6.31.</note> ought ſo to love his Neighbor. If any ſhould object that this brotherly kindneſs, was only to be exerciſed amongſt thoſe of Affinity or Conſanguinity, the 33 and 34 Verſes of the ſame Chapter, remove that reſtraint, ſaying: And if a Stranger ſojourn with thee in your Land, ye ſhall not vex him, but the ſtranger that dwelleth with you, ſhall be unto you as one born amongſt you, <hi>And thou ſhalt love him as thy ſelf,</hi> &amp;c. here is a door of Fraternity o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the manhood, removing all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of pretenſe for Partiality, in the diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of Charity and Juſtice one towards another: And this is atteſted by the <hi>Simile</hi> our Saviour put forth of the <hi>Samaritan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 10.36.37.</note> that did good to him that was fallen among Theeves, and therefore was his neighbor, not reſpecting Allenation of people, but
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153255:10"/>the neceſſity of the Object. Now that men are not ſuch ſtrangers in nature as (by their cruelty and mercileſneſs to each other) they make themſelves. Let them take that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives of their extract, in the <hi>Acts</hi> chapter 17. verſe 26. <hi>And hath made of one Blood, all Nations of men for to dwell on all the face of the Barth,</hi> &amp;c. We count it unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural among Beaſts, that individuals of the ſame ſpecies ſhould prey one upon another: yet with them its leſs practiſed then with men. With what conſcience then can a Creditor (if his light be not become darkneſs) perſue his Debtor to a Priſon? at once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſting him of all the benefit of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, raviſhing all his hopes of improvement in his Generation, damnifying all his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or acquired parts to that end, and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly plunging his Vital and Animal Being into a decay and miſerable languiſhment, which produceth his <hi>Exit</hi> to the World, his debt ſatisfied, and very probably his Creditor to anſwer for his blood: Let all diſintereſſed men judge, if this be not the worſt way of murdering a man.</p>
            <p>By the Law of Charity, no man ought to have ſuch thoughts of another, that being able, he will chooſe a Priſon to avoid paying his Debts; and if in matter of Fact, there be here and there a Monſter in their kind, what
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153255:10"/>may be juſtifiable againſt ſuch an one, the ſeverity of Law being intended for ſuch, ought not to extend to all, that in ſome other fence may ſee culpable in the eye of it; the ſame meaſure may be excuſable to one, that may be criminal, being meeted to another, from the different merit in the recipient. There are doubtleſs many men, to whom the apprehenſions of a Priſon may be more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, then of Death, who therefore being rigorouſly proſecuted by their Creditors may (out of juſt ends, foreſeeing an impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ever making ſatisfaction there) ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle hard, making what defence they can, to prevent ſuch approaching Miſchief and Ruin, (hoping ſtill there may be ſome life in that Proverb, <hi>Multa cadunt inter poculum &amp; labra,</hi> many things fall between the Cup and the Lips, and give a diverſion to ſo violent a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt; which procraſtination feeds only the inſtruments of the Law, leſſens the ſuſtenance and ſolvenry of the Debtors; aggravates the Creditors Account, leaves him to learn by his inconſiderate raſhneſs.</p>
            <p>There are ſome men yet more inveterately tinged with their blood-thirſty and reveng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Spirit, then any before ſpoken off, who not content with their full blow at their Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors liberty, and the conſumption of their lives: being envious at the leaſt ſupport they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153255:11"/>may have in ſo miſerable an eſtate, provide to intercept that alſo, by a Statute of <hi>Bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt</hi> againſt them; thereby not only damning their preſent ſubſiſtance, but extending to that which hath no viſible being, (but may be, in the womb of Providence, and future manifeſtation:) and hath no better aſpect, then a preſumption to affront God Almighty in his goodneſs, for the releif or reſtoration of thoſe that are ſo diſtreſſed and oppreſſed. One of the greateſt enemies to mankind, was doubtleſs in the contrivance of ſo great a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheif to the humane Race: for not one in ten that have been proſecuted, ever anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the end of the Creditors, and irrevocably ruined the Debtors; This and many the like oppreſſions between the Subjects (through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny foul practiſers at Law, Fomenters of their Feuds, and Leeches of their labours, hath been no ſmall cauſe of ſuch a tempeſt of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of late years precipitated upon this Nation. That they have Law to encourage them, is the complaint of the Preacher <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes</hi> 4.1 <hi>So I returned and conſidered all the oppreſſions that are done under the Sun: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the tears of ſuch as were oppreſſed and they had no Comforter; and on the ſide of their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors there was power, but they had no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are ſome that boaſt themſelves in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153255:11"/>the ſucceſs they have had in this fort of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: they no leſs then <hi>Cain,</hi> deſerve a mark that all men may know them by, and avoid. Then penalty for Theft, under the Old Law, was not be exacted, if committed meerly to ſatisfy hunger; and the whole Law is tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butary and reducible to that of Charity; but theſe men (for a ſmall treſpaſs, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto themſelves are in ſome ſenſe acceſſary, there being a reciprocation, between buyer and ſeller, borrower and lender, and are the mutual cauſe of thoſe denominations) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the countenance of a Law, do greedily ſtrip their Debtors of all manner of ſuſtenance, both for preſent and in future, flattering themſelves like the Whore in the <hi>Proverbs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Proverbs.</hi> 7.</note> that they are all the while doing a Sacrafice to Juſtice, when it is only to their own Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable and inſatiable Luſts, and juſtly fall under the deſcription of that Text, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 14.12. <hi>There is a way which ſeemeth right unto a man, but the end thereof if the way of Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeveral Statutes which mainly (if not only,) give motion to ſo barbarous a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Creditors with their Debtors: are the 13. <hi>Eliza.</hi> 7. the 1. <hi>Jacob.</hi> 15. and 21. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob.</hi> 19. which no doubt proceeded then from good intent, to make men Juſt, which all humane Laws can never do, if Juſtice be not firſt written in the heart; no more then the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153255:12"/>avenge of Murder by cruel circumſtances to Death, can deterr the blood-thirſty from <hi>Homicide;</hi> what then might be thought convenient and reaſonable, may be now unprofitable and burthenſome; different ages, produce different intereſts, ways and means of living; what might be reputed cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable then, may now, by a different end, be honeſt and juſt. And if the conſtitutive qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications of a <hi>Bankrupt</hi> by thoſe Statutes, be well conſidered, and compared with the various alteration of Trade, and general oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences to mens Eſtates ſince there will be more need for the Abolition or at leaſt the mitigation of them, then their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. As for inſtance in that of the 21. <hi>Jac.</hi> 19. there is this Qualification of a <hi>Bankrupt</hi>
               <q>Or being indebted to any perſon or perſons in the ſumm of 100 <hi>l.</hi> or more, ſhall not pay, or otherwiſe compound for the ſame, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſix Moneths, next after the ſame ſhall grow due;</q>) When in my knowledge and experience of Trade, the habit thereof hath been ſo much altered for ſome years before and ſince the Dreadful Fire of <hi>London,</hi> that by that qualification, moſt of the Traders in <hi>England,</hi> may be made <hi>Bankrupts,</hi> a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome being introduced, of buying at three or ſix moneths, and paying at ſix, nine, twelve eighteen Moneths, or more. Beſides, the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153255:12"/>exceſs of ſeverity in theſe Statutes, is very evident, as alſo their inequality: other Laws enough, giving the Creditors leave to purſue and force his Debtor to Priſon: and theſe, to cut his throat for being there; too hard to be allowed, that the Creditor ſhall occaſion the matter of Fact, which ſhall render his Debtor the more criminal, and then puniſh him for it; it is like being Judge and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner alſo, in his own Cauſe. Moreover, if the end of thoſe Statutes be deliberated, we ſhall find the Proſecutors much abuſing them; the diſtinguiſhing character of a <hi>Bankrupt,</hi> guilty of the Matters then expreſt, is, <q>to the intent or purpoſe to defraud or hinder any of his or her Creditors, of the juſt debt or duty of ſuch Creditors or Creditors, ſhall be reputed, deemed and taken for a <hi>Bankrupt.</hi>
               </q> Which implies that others may do the ſame Facts, but not to the ſame intent or purpoſe: elſe that ſupplement of words, would be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unneceſſary. But without regard to the ſaid diſtinction the Executioners of theſe Statutes, make uſe of them indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon all perſons within cogniſance of either of the qualifications, to render them a Prey to the gulf of their own particular gain; at once undoing the Debtor, and ſpunging the Creditors malitious excrements. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in a more general way, yet applicable enough to this, gives Teſtimony againſt it,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153255:13"/>by <hi>Obediah</hi> the Prophet, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>Thou ſhouldſt not have entred into the Gate of my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the day of their calamity; yea thou ſhouldſt not have looked on their Affliction in the day of their Calamity; nor have laid hanas on their ſubſtance in the day of their calamity.</hi> The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny general Calamities that of late years and times have befallen this Nation, may very well Apologize, that the inevitable diſability, not the deſigned diſhoneſty of men, may have rendred them lyable to the laſh of thoſe Statutes; and ſo much the more worth the notice of the Great Council of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to redreſs, in whoſe power it is.</p>
            <p>The Premiſes conſidered, the Priſoner is in no better capacity then as dead to his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor, and in no probability, while ſo, ever to ſatisfy him; I would then propound to the Creditor, whether he can be in worſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if he ſet the Debtor free: in ſo doing, he will certainly be better, upon the account of charity; and it is poſſible, the Debtor by his liberty, may attain to make him plenary ſatisfaction here; every age abounding with ſuch examples. Admitting theſe have the aſpects of two Evils expoſed to a man, moſt prudent men agree, 'tis ſafeſt to chooſe the leaſt. Waving the innumeration of a cloud of Scriptures, in the Old Teſtament, that ſpeak in the commendation and approbation
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153255:13"/>of mercifulneſs and the fruits of it, thus applied in particular; I ſhall proceed to inſtance how ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it is to Chriſtianity, and how vigorouſly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and enjoyned in the Doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles. Now for our full conviction: that Article in the Lords Prayer, may be moſt proper lead the Van, <hi>viz. Forgive us our Treſpaſſes, as we forgive them, that treſpaſs againſt us:</hi> ſome Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations have it, <hi>Forgive us our Debts, as we forgive our Debtors:</hi> as in <hi>Matthew</hi> 6.12. reinforcing it, verſes the 14. and 15. <hi>For if ye forgive men their Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſſes, your Heavenly Father will alſo forgive you. But if you forgive not men their Treſpaſſes, neither will your Father forgive your treſpaſſes.</hi> Moſt Theologiſts conſent in this, that men ought to pardon the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniary Debts of their diſabled Debtors. And ſo far will vindicate the purport of what is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed: and without controverſy ſo to remit, is a duty incumbent on all Chriſtians, from the precited Texts: with what impudence then, can men, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſuch as would be reputed Chriſtians, ask God Almighty remiſſion of their own Sins and at the ſame time, detain their Debtor in Gaol, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſuit or Action. The conſideration of the more freedome of acceſs to Heaven by petition, hath ſo far operated upon ſome, in a tumultuous Trade in the World, as to occaſion their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of men, and thereupon conſiderable loſſes to themſelves: but very probably may be remote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comprehended in number with thoſe that ſuffer for Chriſts ſake, being done in obedience to his Doctrine and Spirit; ſuch Loſs will certainly be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153255:14"/>Crowned with infinite Gain. The worſt Epithite that can be aſcribed to a Debt in treſpaſs, is injury and wrong to his Neighbor, and the more voluntary it is, the more aggravated and criminal, <hi>viz.</hi> in thoſe that can pay and will not; Yet, even to thoſe, I find no exceptions provided in our Saviours Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Pardon, but rather the more vehemently urged, as the offence is more provoking; thereby commending to us, the attainment of the beſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of a Chriſtian Eſtate; to this end, thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſeem directed, <hi>viz. Luke</hi> 6.35, 36, 37, and 38. <hi>But love ye your Enemies, and do good, and lend, hoping for nothing again: and your reward ſhall be great, and ye ſhall be the Children of the Higheſt: for he is kind unto the unthankful, and to the evil. Be ye therefore merciful, as your Father alſo is merciful. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, and ye ſhall be forgiven. Give, and it ſhall be given unto you. Good meaſure, preſſed down, and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken together, and running over, ſhall men give into your boſom. For with the ſame meaſure that ye meet withal, it ſhaell be meaſured to you again.</hi> The like in <hi>Matthew</hi> the 5.44, 45, verſes and to the end. The more inconſiſtant this Doctrine ſeems to mens Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Intreſt: it is with the greater difficulty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but is comprehended under ſelf-denial, wherewith the Chriſtian life ſo much abounds. There is a remarkable Emphaſis put upon that Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor mentioned by Our Saviour Chriſt. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.41, 42. that had two Debtors, and when they had no pay, he (frankly) forgave both. That in the l8th. <hi>Matthew</hi> verſe 21. unto the end, runs paralel in kind; reproaching him that had received
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153255:14"/>forgiveneſs, and afterward uſed violence to his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Servant, for a much more inconſiderable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and what became of him is obvious, Verſe 34. <hi>And his Lord was wroth, and delivered him to the Tormentors,</hi> &amp;c. The uſe of inſtruction our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour makes of it, is in Verſe 35. <hi>So likewiſe ſhall my Heavenly Father do alſo unto you, if ye from your hearts forgive not everyone his Brother their Treſpaſſes.</hi> Theſe Scriptures do plainly preſs and enjoyn us to the exerciſe of forbearance, compaſſion and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs towards Debtors, without reſpect of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, honeſt or diſhoneſt, able or diſable, asking it, or not asking it; Much more doubtleſs, do they operate to thoſe that would be Juſt, but are diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and become Petitioners for it, and whoſe condition indeed may ſcarcely merit the Inſcription of a treſpaſs upon it. St. <hi>Paul</hi> is very poſitive and particular in his reproof of litigiouſneſs, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.7. Now therefore there is utterly a fault among you, becauſe ye go to Law one with another, why do ye not rather take wrong? why do you not rather ſuffer your ſelves to be defrauded? as if he were equally ſenſible of the Havock they would make of their worldly Intereſt, in their going to Law: as the violation of Divine Precepts would in their eternal. It is enough notorious that Clyents do meerly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and enrich their various Agents at Law, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſeveral officers appending the Courts of Judicature; all which exciſe a cauſe equivalently to the matter in controverſy, called by them the merit of the Cauſe; ſo that the Clyents like a cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Souldier, may only be ſaid to be run the Gante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lope
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153255:15"/>amongſt them: I mean the diſhoneſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful practiſers and agents in the Law. Without excep ion, the Laws given to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> were Free and full enough for the diſtribution and ſupport of Property: but the <hi>Labyrinth</hi> ſince erected by men upon them, ſavours more of Arrogance, as if God the fountain of Wiſdom, were deficient in his Laws, Government or bridle upon the evil nature, and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mens ſupplements (a tincture of the lapſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, that would pretend to mend the ways and Councel of God) then any zeal, goodneſs or Piety to the Creation.</p>
            <p>Let us leave off therefore our Cruelty, Oppreſſion, Violence, Covetouſneſs and Revenge one towards another, and follow the advice given us by Holy men, and Jeſus Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>The Preacher in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> the 11.1, and 2. <hi>verſes;</hi> Caſt thy bread upon the waters, for thou ſhalt find it after many days. Give a Portion to ſeven, and alſo to eight; for thou knoweſt not what evil ſhall be upon the Earth; making that an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for improving the preſent time to do good in, and to diſtribute: namely, the revolution of time and providence, that doth remove extreams to one and the ſame Subject; making him poor and needy, that was wealthy and did abound, and ſo, <hi>è con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra:</hi> the greater reaſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 6.10</note> we ſhould do good with it, whilſt it may be called Ours.</p>
            <p>Let us avoid alſo that character, which is given them who ſhew no favour: <hi>Proverbs.</hi> 2.10. The ſoul of the wicked deſireth evil: his neighbour find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no favour in his eyes. And <hi>Proverbs</hi> 22.22,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153255:15"/>and 23 <hi>verſes.</hi> Rob not the poor becauſe they are poor: neither oppreſs the afflicted in the Gate: for the Lord will plead their cauſe, and ſpoile the ſoul of thoſe that ſpoiled them. It is a uſual thing for many to fall upon a man already in Priſon; which I believe is reprehended in the foregoing Text: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oppreſs the afflicted in the Gate: that is ſuch upon whom the Law hath already paſſed; the ſeat of Judicature, being often in Scripture repreſented under the denomination of the Gate. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.13. Whoſo ſtopeth his Ears at the cry of the Poor, he alſo ſhall cry himſelf, but ſhall not be heard. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.17. He that hath pitty upon the Poor, lendeth unto the Lord: and look what he layeth out, it ſhall be pay'd him again. Let us alſo eſcape the Judgement that is denounced againſt the mercileſs. <hi>James</hi> 2.13. For he ſhall have Judgement without mercy, that hath ſhewed no mercy <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now that I may not ſeem partial in my diſcourſe, only to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the Creditor his duty; I ſhall indeavour alſo to leave the Debtor inexcuſable, and ſhew him his duty, which is incumbent upon him, by the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Divine Laws: as that upon the Creditor.</p>
            <p>Let not the Debtor think ever a whit the better of himſelf, by what is foreſpoken to the Creditor: for he is no leſs guilty of the breach of divine Laws, and contempt of the like admonitions: if he fail in one title of Juſtice, that is within his power or contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to performe; Therefore the 8th. Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteal,</hi> and thereunder Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects all the divers ways and modes of injuſtice, whereby a man may prejudiſe or leſſen the eſtate of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153255:16"/>his neighbor, or therewith benefit himſelf. This exceedingly digreſſeth from that Royal rule, <hi>Matthew</hi> 7.12. Therefore all things whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them: for this is the Law and the Prophets.</p>
            <p>The Debtor ought to deal with his Creditor, as himſelf would be dealt with, if he were a Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor? and men are to behave themſelves towards others, no otherwiſe, then ſuppoſing themſelves to be the ſubject of their own Actions: It this Rule were obſerved, there would be but little cruelty, tearing or devouring one another: and as little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice to provoke it. <hi>Solomon</hi> in <hi>Proverbs</hi> 3.27, 28. giveth ſuitable Advice: Withhold not good from them to whom it is due, when it is in the power of thine hand to do it. Say not unto thy neighbor, go, and come again, and to morrow I will give, when thou haſt it by thee. This councel complicates the mutual duty of Creditor and Debtor: and if men did not idolize the things of this world, they would never exchange their birth-right to virtue and eternal Happineſs; for the pottage of this life. Let the Debtor therefore, conſider the hazard that he runs, to deceive or injure his Creditor: it is at the leaſt a great Ecclipſe (if not total extinction,) of his Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in everlaſting Glory, if not timely repented of, and reſtitution made, if within his power: the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Law being as a devouring fire, that ceaſeth not, untill the ſin be conſumed; The Story of <hi>Zacheus, Luke</hi> 19.8. is very exemplary herein, <hi>viz. Zacheus</hi> ſtood forth, and ſaid unto the Lord, behold Lord! the half of my goods I give to the Poor, and if I
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153255:16"/>have done any wrong to any man, I reſtore four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. St. <hi>Paul Corinth.</hi> 1.6.8, and 9. <hi>verſes,</hi> is very expreſs in his reproof herein, urging the ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> Nay, you do wrong and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud, and that your Brethren, Know you not that the unrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is an Argument of the greateſt force, to diſwade men from doing injuſtice, when the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Kingdom of God is forfeited thereby; although it ſhould produce never ſo great gain here, yet our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Matthew</hi> 16.26. <hi>For what is a man profitted, if he ſhall gain the whole World, and loſe his own Soul?</hi> Farthermore, it ſavoureth greatly of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, which is hardly pardonable with men: for a man to requite any truſt with infidelity; it invades humane Society, and is attended with numerous aggravations, whereby to render it odious and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable.</p>
            <p>Finally I ſhall conclude with impartial Advice, both to Creditor and Debtor: Let not the firſt flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter themſelves that all is well, when they have uſed their will upon their Debtors, according to the ſcope that humane Laws give them; and have pay'd themſelves, perhaps with the ruin of their Debtors, or without; it is much alike in Scriptural conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they have attained it uncharitably, unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and violently, and are reſponſible for it unto God Almighty: and may perad venture go wilfully ignorant to Hell, with ſuch a Crime unrepented of.</p>
            <p>There is no Creditor, but in his proſecution, is hurried therein by ſome devilliſh luſt or other, as Covetouſneſs, Extortion, Pride or Envy, and ſuch
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153255:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. Neither let the Debtor think himſelf ſecure, if he can do injuſtice or defraud his Creditor undiſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: or abuſe his patience, or forbearance exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed towards him, in ſenſe of his duty required by God; for without Repentance and ſatisfaction, he ſhall not eſcape the Judgment of God.</p>
            <p>Let us all therefore conſider our wayes, in either of the ſaid capacities, as Creditor or Debtor, or both: that we are accomptable to the Laws of Heaven, for our good or ill behaviour therein one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, as moſt certainly comprehended in his Commandements; And we ſhall incline our ſelves more to follow the Apoſtles advice, to ſtudy and follow peace with all men, and perſwade there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, ſo we ſhall be entituled to that bleſſedneſs, pronounced by Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Bleſſed are the Peace-makers, for they ſhall be called the Children of God.</hi> Neither ſhall our livelyhoods be any longer a prey to thoſe that have ſold themſelves to this World, and live by mens litigious Conteſts.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
